Guide to the Robert J. T. Joy Student Notes from Yale School of Medicine
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Robert J. T. Joy Student Notes from Yale School of Medicine
1950-1954
Ms Coll 18
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1
(2 boxes)
Robert J. T. Joy graduated from Yale School of Medicine in 1954. The collection contains his student notes.
Joy, Robert J. T.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Robert J. T. Joy, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Robert J. T. Joy received his B.S. from the University of Rhode Island in 1950 and graduated from the Yale School of Medicine in 1954. He trained in internal medicine at the Walter Reed General Hospital in Washington, D.C. Joy served in the army from 1954 to 1981, rising to the rank of colonel. He was commander of the Walter Reed Army Institute of Research Team in Vietnam and later Director of the WRAIR. In 1976 he founded the department of military medicine at the Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences and served as first Commandant. When he retired from the Army, he founded the USUHS section (later a department) of medical history which he headed until 1996.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of Robert J. T. Joy's student notebooks from Yale School of Medicine containing handwritten illustrated notes and mimeograph pages from medical school lectures and laboratories. Among the subjects covered are anatomy, bacteriology, biochemistry, genetics, histology, neuroanatomy, pathology, pharmacology, physical diagnosis, and physiology. In his letter of transmittal, Dr. Joy noted some of the professors who had taught these courses.
Arrangement
Notebooks are arranged alphabetically by subject with clinical notes at the end.
Medical education; Lecture notes; Medical students; Physicians; Medical historians; Barron, Donald Henry, 1905-1993; Bunting, Henry, 1911-1954; Burr, Harold Saxton, 1889-; Forbes, Thomas Rogers, 1911-1988; Fruton, Joseph S. (Joseph Stewart), 1912-2007; Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960; Gardner, William U. (William Ullman), 1907-1988; Greene, Harry Sylvestre Nutting, 1904-1969; Liebow, Averill A., 1911-; Weinman, David, 1909-1991; Yale University. School of Medicine; Yale University. School of Medicine. Class of 1954
- Anatomy and neuroantomy, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Two notebooks. Dr. Joy noted that gross anatomy was taught by Thomas R. Forbes and William U. Gardiner and neuroanatomy by Harold S. Burr.
- Anatomy review notes (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Neuroanatomy laboratory, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bacteriology, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bacteriology laboratory, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Physiological chemistry (Biochemistry), 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Two notebooks. The department changed names from Physiological Chemistry to Biochemistry in 1950.
- Physiological chemistry (Biochemistry) laboratory, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Mimeographed sheets. Dr. Joy noted that Joseph Fruton was one of the teachers of biochemistry.
- Biochemistry review notes (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Genetics, medical etymology, and endocrinology, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Dr. Joy noted that Donald Henry Barron taught endocrine physiology.
- Histology, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Pathology, notebooks I and II, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Dr. Joy noted that Averill Liebow, Harry Greene, and Henry Bunting had taught the pathology course.
- Pathology, notebook III, and Pathology laboratory, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Two notebooks.
- Pharmacology, notebooks I and II, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Pharmacology, notebook III, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Physical diagnosis, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Includes lectures on hematology.
- Physiology, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Notebook on physiology and loose pages on the nervous system. Dr. Joy noted that this was John F. Fulton's last year of teaching neurophysiology.
- Clinical notes, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  These are sheets removed by Dr. Joy from pocket-size binders.